Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组 Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Today's rites honor the seventh week since Consort Vietu's death.
How are the preparations going?
All complete.
Baohua Hall has already started the ritual.
But I've been thinking
a ritual alone is not enough to console Vertu's spirit in Heaven.
At that time, you ordered that Jingbai and Feiwen
be executed by flogging.
I no longer find that sufficient.
Gūwalgiya stirred up disharmony in the harem,
while her father “created winds and waves” in the court.
Those two are "rats and serpents from the same den."
Are they putting our entire family on the path to damnation?
I know you are displeased,
but with the harem and the court ...
“when you pull a single hair, it affects the whole body.”
This matter cannot be rushed.
Isn't your name Yurao?
Your Majesty already knows that.
The character 娆 [rao] means enchanting and soft.
The name is beautiful,
but it doesn't match your fiery personality.
Women should be gentle and even-tempered.
How about I grant you the name Yurissé?
I don't mind the name Yurissé, but remind me where it comes from.
After all, Your Majesty can't arbitrarily pick a name
and give it to my third sister.
"Yurissé displayed the beauty of grace and gentleness,
and nurtured feelings of caring tenderness."
From "Poem of the Eternal Reminiscence" by Zhang Hua.
This is a line praising the beautiful lady. What do you think?
"The fair lady's beauty was enchanting;
she could level a city with an affectionate glance."
The "Poem of the Eternal Reminiscence"
was written to mourn the deceased.
I am alive and standing right before Your Majesty.
I was only drawing an analogy.
“She brought me unsurpassed joy,
and united with me in heart and mind."
"Our bond was strong and deep,
so was our love and connection.”
Zhang Hua wrote this poem to mourn his late wife.
Your Majesty can't be ...
intending to take Yurao as your wife?
In the harem, the distinction is particularly clear
between wife and concubines.
The wife is the Empress - the head of the harem.
I don't have that intention.
However...
I lack blessings and virtues.
I am willing to serve Your Majesty as a concubine my entire life.
However, Yurao has too much pride.
She cannot be a concubine and serve by someone's side.
Even though you are my concubine, you are my favorite one.
And you are the distinguished Noble Consort,
second only to the Empress.
If your sister gains the same honor, that would not be a mistreatment.
Although my second sister Yuyin is loved by Lord XVII,
she is only the Lord Consort.
For myself, I do not covet the throne of the Empress.
But Your Majesty ...
can you bear seeing all of my sisters become secondary wives?
I was just thinking of an honorary name for her.
I did not mean to upset you.
Clearly I was too rash.
Yurissé is not a fitting name.
We shall not speak of it again.
Your sister is still young.
One day I will find a match for her from a deserving family.
I will watch out for her.
Let's stop talking about this now.
I witnessed great misfortune in my family when I was young.
Your Majesty asked about my unyielding personality.
If Your Majesty heard of the incidents in my childhood,
how my parents and I journeyed north to Ningguta
and suffered all kinds of hardships,
Your Majesty would understand.
I am willing to listen.
His Majesty departs.
I bid Your Majesty farewell.
His Majesty did not say anything.
He just gave this to me,
and said he will retrieve it in a few days.
This jade pendant of a pair of mandarin ducks...
His Majesty always wears it close to his body.
That's why, elder sister, I can't keep this.
His Majesty cherishes this pendant most dearly.
Yurao.
It is probably because you look so much like Empress Première.
I can only be Zhen Yurao.
There can be only one of me, not two.
I can never be a substitute for someone else.
Good.
That's the daughter of our Zhen family!
Your Majesty, it's time to take some rest,
or you may grow tired in the afternoon.
Your Majesty, where is your jade pendant?
It's missing.
I gave it to Yurao.
My Third Lady?
What's the matter?
Nothing. I just think she is quite blessed,
because that jade pendant was treasured by Empress Première.
That means she's blessed?
Her days of blessings are yet to come.
Go light the benzoin incense.
Aye.
I heard that His Majesty
is investigating the Gūwalgiyas on account of Délice's offense.
He uncovered her father's years of crimes
including defaming officials, colluding in fractions,
taking bribes,
and exercising excessive cruelty.
In just about a month,
their properties have been seized,
and their families imprisoned or banished.
His Majesty has been busy at court,
and neither have our ears been idle.
Gūwalgiya Emin has committed suicide in prison.
Evidently, His Majesty was not unaware
of their crimes.
But with court affairs ...
"when you pull a single hair, it affects the whole body."
One must not act recklessly.
That being the case, one strategy is to delay interference.
But considering His Majesty's actions of late,
he is likely intending to uproot the Gūwalgiyas.
Slow actions won't bring any quick results.
If their crimes are not exposed all at once,
how can they be "caught in a single net" and eliminated completely?
Délice is foolish and impertinent,
and her father is no better.
When His Majesty's orders came down like a thunderbolt,
they were inevitably caught off guard.
Your Majesty.
Your Majesty the Empress!
Your ...
Your Majesty.
Stop!
-Your Majesty!
-Stop!
Stop running!
-Your...
-Stop!
--Stop running!
-Your Majesty!
Your Majesty!
Gūwalgiya begs for an audience with Her Majesty the Empress!
Stop!
Of the Gūwalgiya family,
behead all the adult men,
banish those under fourteen to the Western Front,
and confiscate all the women to be slaves of other officials.
Your Majesty,
I beg of you to pardon my family.
Please spare my maiden family, Your Majesty!
Your Majesty!
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
Tell Gūwalgiya that
considering her many years of service,
I will only demote her to a commoner.
I won't grant her suicide.
Send her back.
Aye.
Your Majesty, I beg you to pardon my family.
Living like this is no better than death for me!
Your Majesty, that bitch blinded your trust!
You wrongfully convicted your loyal subjects!
Zhen Huan! You bitch!
I won't spare you even after I die!
Come out, Zhen Huan!
Why are you all standing here watching?
Quick, get rid of her.
Aye. Aye.
Let's go.
Zhen Huan! You bitch!
I won't spare you even when I become a ghost!
I will become a ghost to haunt you!
Bury the body in a mass grave.
Don't bother His Majesty with this.
It would soil His Majesty's ears.
Aye.
I will write another decree to exonerate your father
and reinstate his position.
Your Majesty,
please don't grant my father a lofty post.
He is growing old.
Then I'll make him the official of ceremonies at the fourth rank,
so he can spend his remaining years in peace.
I thank Your Majesty.
Do you know why she died miserably?
I don't, Your Majesty.
Because she was useless.
In the harem, an incapable woman has no way out but death.
And the capable women can be quite difficult to deal with.
We must be more careful.
Yes.
Elder sister, why didn't you interrogate Délice
and make her confess that the Empress was the mastermind?
She would be too fearful that the Empress would then
execute all survivors of the Gūwalgiya clan.
And she hated me to the core.
Why would she have wanted to implicate
the only woman who can constrain me?
Over the years, His Lordship collected proof of
many instances of the Gūwalgiyas' crimes.
Now we finally had the chance to use it.
Lord XVII is your husband.
It's only natural that he helps his in-laws.
Since you live outside of the palace,
I hope you and His Lordship can look after our family.
Rest assured, elder sister.
His Lordship devoted himself to helping us
because you show dedication to his estate.
Are you getting along with Meng Jingxian?
Has she given you a hard time?
How could she?
Although her health is improving,
she still has to drink ginseng soup daily.
His Lordship shows pity towards her, so she is well provided for.
But they have little to talk about.
His Lordship has no affection towards her
while you have known His Lordship for years.
You always make fun of me.
But you are right. His Lordship treats me well.
Elder sister, I'm going to go out.
Our third sister is so beautifully dressed.
Where is she going?
I have no idea.
It's not easy to keep a grown girl at home.
Yesterday I heard from His Lordship that
Venerable Prince Shen ran into Yurao
when he came to visit the Empress Dowager.
And for whatever reason,
both of them blushed upon seeing each other.
The Empress Dowager was also surprised.
Since when has this been going on?
What do you mean?
I'm asking about you and Venerable Prince Shen.
About...
I don't remember.
Don't you mind his mother's humble background?
He never considered my background.
I remember someone once said that
"I'd rather live a coarse life with a commoner
than marry into any imperial palace or estate."
I wonder who said that?
Stop teasing me, elder sister.
Yunxi is different from His Majesty.
He is nice.
If you two are serious,
I can ask about His Majesty's opinion.
But promise me that you won't meet with him in secret.
People will gossip and laugh.
All right.
Yuyin, I take my leave now.
Have you made up your mind, elder sister?
We both can see His Majesty is interested in Yurao.
We may as well marry Yurao off before things get difficult.
I've considered that
it won't be helpful if Yurao marries into an ordinary family.
But if Yurao is married to one of his own brothers,
it will end His Majesty's hopes.
Otherwise, we will have endless trouble.
It's just as well.
Fortunately, Yurao and Lord Shen are attached to each other,
which makes things much easier.
It's just that there are only a few concubines in the harem now,
so His Majesty's eyes are fixed on Yurao.
We need to find a way to divert His Majesty's attention.
Elder sister, you may entrust this to me.
Lotus, for how long have you served His Lordship?
Five or six years.
Has His Lord treated you well?
His Lordship has bestowed upon me
"kindness as weighty as a mountain."
And do you know about His Lordship's situation in the palace?
His Majesty has many brothers,
but only few of them are treated with deference.
Some were stripped of their titles, and some were imprisoned.
A disaster could overwhelm any of them at any time.
His Majesty hasn't shown mercy even to his own brothers.
Your Ladyship...
Come here.
Because we are outside the palace
we don't know His Majesty's inclinations.
But what if someone from our estate
were close to His Majesty's heart
and could please him with honeyed words?
Then our estate would be better protected, wouldn't it?
Your Ladyship is suggesting that ...
I could shoulder such a great task.
You can.
You are the fairest in His Lordship's estate and the Cooling Terrace.
Moreover, you are loyal to His Lordship.
I can't entrust this to anyone but you.
I ...
If you are truly grateful for His Lordship's kindness,
you should act in the interests of the whole estate.
Trust me,
His Majesty will appreciate how beautiful you are.
I ...
I will follow Your Ladyship's orders.
Your Noble Highness might not have heard
the news about Concubine An's father.
He was reported for taking bribes of
eight hundred thousand taels and several estates.
This time, His Majesty is outraged.
Really? You telling me is the first I've heard of it.
Yes, everyone in the harem is laughing about it.
In Your Noble Highness's eyes,
this bird is appreciated for its snow-white feathers.
But in An Bihuai's eyes, each feather would have to be
a silver tael to be beautiful!
Joie, you're never short on wit.
"In three years, even an honest village magistrate
amasses bribes of a hundred thousand taels."
And An Bihuai is "the nation's father-in-law."
Eight hundred thousand taels are nothing to him.
An Bihuai honored himself as
"the nation's father-in-law" to fool the dolts.
His Majesty doesn't consider him as the father-in-law.
He is now deposed and detained.
As long as his daughter is in favor,
no one would care about whether
he was truly "the nation's father-in-law."
It was clever of you
to have your father keep an eye on him
and expose his weaknesses.
Otherwise, Concubine An would grow too proud.
Were it not for Your Highness's far-sighted plan,
I wouldn't have had a use for this leverage.
His Majesty is furious with the Gūwalgiya clan right now.
Why did An Bihuai have to barrel into this mess?
Besides, His Majesty only promoted him to Mayor
on account of Concubine An's favor.
Isn't that a slap to His Majesty's face?
He made himself a laughing stock.
I heard that Concubine An has been pleading with unfastened hair,
kneeling outside the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
She's been crying for the past two days.
Peace and grace to Your Highness.
Mr. Su.
His Majesty summons Your Highness to have dinner
with him later in the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
Your Highness, please.
Understood.
I won't bother Your Highness any longer.
I take my leave.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Follow us to get updates on the translation progress.
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Lingrong, why do you have to do this to yourself?
You should be mindful about your health.
Would you deny me the right
to "plead with unfastened hair"?
It's not that.
I'm just worried that it'll be windy and humid during the late night.
What if you catch a cold,
or
a rat scurries out and bites you,
giving you the plague?
I know you're joking.
How can there be rats near the Hall of Mental Cultivation?
Yes,
I forgot.
You would only find such creatures in a prison.
My concern was mistaken.
I shouldn't have worried about you,
but rather,
worried for your father.
Peace and grace to Your Highness.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
I've been waiting for you for a while.
I saw Lingrong kneeling outside, very pitifully.
I tried to talk her out of it.
How could she listen?
Right now, she's only thinking about her decadent father.
I granted him the promotion to Mayor.
How dare he squander my favor and make me lose face!
Your Majesty, don't be angry.
An Bihuai's wrongdoing is his own,
it has nothing to do with Concubine An.
Would Your Majesty let her rise?
I never wanted to punish her.
She chose to kneel and plead for her father,
which is most improper.
Concubine An is desperate to save her father.
Your Majesty, don't blame it on her, please.
Will Your Majesty spare An Bihuai?
Why would I?
I will neither take my anger out on her,
nor spare An Bihuai for her sake.
She hasn't been eating or drinking for two days,
nor has she slept.
Is Your Majesty not worried about her?
Committing suicide is a serious crime for a concubine,
which would implicate her family.
She would not dare.
Your Majesty.
Dressed in white with her makeup removed,
Concubine An is even more entrancing than usual.
But what a shame...
Why?
White is clean, and the purest color.
It should not be woven with one's desire.
Twisted with desire,
the inherent purity of whiteness is tarnished.
The night is getting cold. Send Concubine An back.
Your Majesty!
I will keep An Bihuai imprisoned.
If you plead any more,
I will have him executed.
Your Majesty...
Your Majesty!
I beg of Your Majesty to save my father.
I'm afraid that despite my inclination to help you, I am powerless.
If Your Majesty would only lend me a helping hand,
I would die for Your Majesty a thousand times with no regrets.
Your Majesty!
It is not that I don't want to help you.
I'm afraid that, this time, you must rely on yourself.
I beg Your Majesty to enlighten me about the right path.
His Majesty is benevolent and places great importance on his children.
You've been serving His Majesty for years
but have never been pregnant.
I have a secret prescription which is extraordinarily effective,
but the herbal dosages can be harsh on your health.
You will regain His Majesty's deep favor if you are pregnant.
Naturally, the favor will extend to your family.
But...
but I was taking the Flesh Thinning Pills.
Even if I could become pregnant,
I may not be able to deliver the child, Your Majesty.
If pregnancy itself is enough to resolve this desperate issue,
it's not necessary that you actually deliver the child.
I heard from Yuyin that
His Majesty is interested in Yurao.
If Noble Consort Lumière intercedes on your behalf,
I hope His Majesty will grant you two marriage.
But what will you do
if His Majesty disapproves?
I'm just a Venerable Prince, almost invisible.
I yearn for nothing in this world
but Yurao.
Yet you need to realize that
we can never contend with His Majesty.
His Majesty can take any lady he wants,
but not their hearts.
Even if I might not succeed,
I will spare no effort.
I lost the woman I loved before,
so I understand your feelings now.
I only need to ask you one thing.
Do you love Yurao wholeheartedly?
"My heart is not a round pebble."
"It cannot turn and change course."
I've known about his feelings early on.
Given his sincerity, it's worth pushing past some setbacks.
I assure you that
we will do anything we can
though not everything is within our control.
We don't want you two
to live with regret for the rest of your lives.
The Empress Dowager's health is precarious now.
We need to make haste.
If Her Majesty were to pass away suddenly,
we would enter three years of national mourning.
"One has more dreams the longer he sleeps."
Elder sister, regarding what you asked me to do,
I've arranged everything.
The new concubine will enter the palace this afternoon.
Who is she?
You know her, it's Lotus.
Why did you choose her?
She is truly blessed.
His Majesty has already granted her the title Companion Lustré.
Your Majesty.
Attendant Services is here.
The one from Noble Prince Guo's estate has arrived?
[Companion Lustré]
Yes, she has moved into the Palace of Eternal Spring.
How does she look?
She was personally selected by Lady Yuyin.
Your Majesty can trust her.
It was very thoughtful of Noble Prince Guo's estate.
Lately, it's been very busy at the imperial court.
I haven't had time to take a walk with you.
So today Your Majesty compensates me with your time?
You are teasing me again.
Did you intentionally bring me here to see this?
I don't need to.
This can be seen every day.
Having strong and deep feelings like this...
Si Lang and Huan Huan have experienced this ourselves.
Why not grant them their wish?
Noble Consort Lumière, you are so clever.
You must have noticed my feelings towards Yurao.
Your Majesty is far more clever than I am.
Your Majesty knows the story of
King Xiang's unrequited love for the goddess Yaoji.
I have my ways.
Even if Your Majesty can find a way,
you should ask Yurao's opinion.
There's nothing to be gained by forcing her.
And Venerable Prince Shen is your own brother.
His Majesty disapproves of us being together.
If my imperial brother won't give us his blessing,
I will keep asking him.
If he still doesn't allow it,
I'll follow in my 17th brother's footsteps
and not get married at all.
No matter what happens, I will live up to our commitment,
and I won't marry anyone else.
I know nothing has been settled.
And you may have many concerns.
But listen when I say,
don't worry.
I understand.
Go to Companion Lustré's place.
Your Majesty has forgotten.
You promoted Companion Lustré to Attendant today.
The ceremony is going on right now.
Never mind then, it won't be over for a while.
Then Your Majesty would like to go to ...?
To the Palace of Prolonging Happiness.
His Majesty left you without a word ...
what does that mean?
I had to show him, no matter what he meant.
I'm afraid that His Majesty could be upset and become angry at Your Highness.
Elder sister.
Look at you. You have beads of sweat all over your face.
Still acting like a child.
Was it nice seeing Venerable Prince Shen today?
Yes.
I'm always happy to see him and talk with him.
I'm glad you're happy.
I hope you'll always be this happy.
Elder sister.
I would do anything
as long as it makes you happy.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Rise.
You were playing "Hymn to a Gentleman."
Is there a gentleman you admire, Yurao?
As a gentleman myself,
I am very fond of Yurao, the zither player.
Is your Majesty fond of me
because of my sister?
Everybody says I resemble my sister.
You resemble her, yet don't resemble her.
You have the beauty
that accompanies fearlessness and daring.
By appearance,
you resemble my wife a lot.
Really?
I don't think I look very similar to the Empress.
She is the Empress, but she is not my wife.
My wife departed this world a long time ago.
I understand.
Your Majesty can have many Empresses,
but only one wife.
You are very clever.
What about my sister?
Your sister is the most important woman by my side.
You have asked me many questions.
Is it because you wish to be my woman, like your sister?
I envy Your Majesty's wife.
Why is that?
Although she left this world too soon,
Your Majesty thinks of her as your only wife.
You think about her often.
Your Majesty said you are fond of me, right?
Yes.
I've had a dream since I was young
to be the wife of the man I love.
Not a concubine, nor the most important woman,
but the one and only wife that he loves.
It's a pity that Your Majesty already has your own wife,
and cannot fulfill my dream.
I hope that one day
I will see my dream come true
instead of living in envy of Your Majesty's wife.
As I said, you are very clever, just like your sister.
This is not cleverness, this is a fact.
Even if your Majesty likes me enough
to make me stay in your harem,
what would that do for me?
Even if you banished the Empress and gave me her palace,
the Empress is only the Empress,
not Your Majesty's true wife.
Please forgive me for speaking so candidly.
Your Majesty and your wife
must have cherished each other dearly.
I feel a strong affinity with Yunxi.
I dare not request Your Majesty to make me Yunxi's primary wife.
Even if I were his concubine, I would be happy.
I only beg your Majesty
to let me be with him.
Don't you only want to become his wife?
Although in name the Empress is Your Majesty's wife,
Your Majesty doesn't consider her to be your wife.
Although in the future,
I may not be Yunxi's wife by name,
but he cherishes only me in his heart
and I him.
I know that he will never marry another woman.
I will be his only love, the only one in his heart.
Doesn't that mean I am his wife?
Rise.
I know that your Majesty is fond of me.
If you are fond of someone, you should fulfill their wish.
Aside from the Empress,
Your Majesty has many women around you.
I haven't been in the palace long,
but long enough to see my sister go through many disturbances.
Although Your Majesty considers my sister
your most important woman,
she is still on her guard every day.
I don't wish to live that kind of life.
Your Majesty's fondness for me is precious.
I dare not squander it.
But fondness need not only be
that between a man and a woman.
I plead with Your Majesty
to treat me with the fondness
you have for a younger sister.
Your Majesty entrusted this item to me.
It returns untarnished to its rightful owner.
I request that Your Majesty fulfill the wish
long cherished by Yunxi and myself.
This jade pendant - I grant it to you as a gift.
Your Majesty, the lamp is already burning low.
It might strain your eyes.
I brought you a new one.
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
There is a lady that I'm fond of,
but she is unwilling to become my concubine.
What do you think?
Your Majesty,
I do not know who this lady is,
but in my mind，
no woman can compare to Empress Première.
What do you mean by that?
I meant,
it does not matter who Your Majesty is fond of.
If this person is able to serve Your Majesty
in the way that Empress Première could,
she must be truly blessed.
Your eyes...
they see things too sharply!
All right, I have a task for you.
Yes, Your Majesty.
The sister of Noble Consort Lumière will get married
following the protocol for a princess of the fourth rank.
She is marrying Yunxi,
whose mother is now promoted to Consort Dowager Harmonie.
The Empress Dowager has been ill for some time.
Let's hope the auspicious events will dispel the evil spirits.
The Noble Consort's sister
marrying the Emperor's brother!
These romantic tales are few and far between.
When the Empress Dowager knows about this,
it will definitely help her condition!
Your Majesty, Your Majesty.
I think my time has come.
Your Majesty, please don't say that!
The imperial doctors are all waiting outside,
I will call them in now.
Bamboo,
this thought persists in my mind,
even when my mind is muddled
while I've been sick.
For the glory of the Ulanara and the Uya clans,
I have always helped the Empress, Yixiu, to keep her throne.
Was I wrong to do so?
Your Majesty,
please don't say that.
I knew Yixiu ...
what she did to Première...
I knew everything
but there was nothing I could do.
If Yixiu dies,
the Ulanara clan will have no one
to succeed to the throne.
I suffered every hardship to become the Empress Dowager.
My efforts in this life cannot be wasted.
So even though I knew
she had been murdering imperial concubines and heirs,
I had no choice but to
protect her and her throne.
Your Majesty repeatedly admonished the Empress,
but she became fixated on her obsessions.
She is the one who has caused so many deaths.
If only she had listened to you and stopped her wrongdoing!
No matter how much I dislike her,
I had to take into account the glory of the entire clan.
These past few days...
I've dreamt of Première night after night.
How deep is my remorse for her!
Your Majesty once said
Empress Première was too kind,
and therefore not suitable as the head of the harem.
Only Yixiu
would not yield her grip on the Empress's throne
to anyone else.
I feel remorseful towards the emperor too
and all of my innocent imperial grandchildren.
But now
I can only advise the Emperor day to day,
but not for the days to come.
I've dedicated my whole life...
Please stop worrying so much, Your Majesty.
Bamboo...
Bring me paper and ink.
I... I have to write down an edict for the future ...
just in case.
Your Majesty, please be mindful of your health.
You must remember
one day when I am no more,
you must keep this edict safe.
If any ...
incident happens to alter the Empress's throne,
you must use my edict to protect Yixiu.
I understand. I will bring some paper.
I will get it.
His Majesty and Her Noble Highness depart!
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
Just now at the table,
you and I,
Yunli and Yuyin,
Yunxi and Yurao
We are three fine couples aligned by the will of Heaven.
My little sister Yurao is beyond grateful to Your Majesty.
I have you by my side.
That's why I was willing to fulfill her wish.
Your Majesty! Your Majesty!
Your Majesty!
Halt!
Your Majesty.
Her Majesty the Empress Dowager...
Her Majesty is in grave condition.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.